<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ambitions scourge Described in the morall fiction of Ixyon. By Sands Penuen.</title>
            <author>Penuen, Sands.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838318</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838318</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2692</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2692)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1111:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ambitions scourge Described in the morall fiction of Ixyon. By Sands Penuen.</title>
                  <author>Penuen, Sands.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Helme, and are to be solde at his shoppe, in S. Dunstons Church-yard in Fleetstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londom [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Ixyon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D² +.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some print show-through, and some pages stained; lacking all after D2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ixion (Greek mythology) --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AMBITION SCOVRGE.</p>
            <p>DESCRIBED IN THE MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALE FICTION OF <hi>IXYON,</hi> BY Sands Penuen.</p>
            <q>Qui deſiderium ſuum c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſit, cum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue de Foelicitate contendit.<bibl>
                  <hi>Senec.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Helme,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe, in S. Dunſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church-yard in Fleetſtrecte. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>R<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, Syr <hi>Michaell Sands,</hi> of <hi>Throughley</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF what is truly Morall, ſerious, graue,</l>
               <l>May (clad in Rimes) but gracious fauour haue:</l>
               <l>From your Right worthy ſelfe, then am I crown'd,</l>
               <l>As if with <hi>Laurell,</hi> for in you abound</l>
               <l>All that make man compleate; t' is you therefore</l>
               <l>That my <hi>Muſe</hi> for her <hi>Patron</hi> doth implore:</l>
               <l>T'was by your meanes that I was firſt inſtructed</l>
               <l>In <hi>Grammer</hi> learning, ſince which time inducted</l>
               <l>To ſome more knowledge, I most humbly pray</l>
               <l>You, to accept this Tributarie pay,</l>
               <l>From him (who though his <hi>Muſe</hi>) bee yet vnnoted,</l>
               <l>Vowes all her ſtudies are to you deuoted.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhould it bee a blemiſh to your Fame,</l>
               <l>To haue theſe <hi>Pages</hi> waite vpon your Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to command, Sa: Penuen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigram">
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:3"/>
            <head>The Author to the Preſſe. Epigram.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Preſſe for Print, is vvorſe then that for Death;</l>
               <l>For that ſtops ill, and this vent's ſtincking breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>To his Friend, <hi>Sa: Penuen,</hi> on his <hi>Ixyon.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IT ſeemes Apollo leades thee to the ſpring,</l>
               <l>Where thou maiſt heare the learned Siſters ſing:</l>
               <l>For by thy liuely vvittes Inuention,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhevv'ſt Ixyons leaud intention.</l>
               <l>Hee hath his merit, puniſhment and ſhame,</l>
               <l>Take thou thy merit, t'is a liuing Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R. Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:3"/>
            <head>R. D. Eſquire, to his reſpected Friend, <hi>Sands Penuen.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF only hee might reade, that knew to write,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Cenſure voyde of <hi>Ignorance</hi> as ſpight:</l>
               <l>Might cheriſh free, or checke: not hee whoſe braine</l>
               <l>Is lighter then his feather, whoſe chiefe ſtraine</l>
               <l>Of wit, conſists in's neate compoſure, fraught</l>
               <l>With nothing but ill face, can me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, cry naught.</l>
               <l>(As best comporting with him) then thy <hi>Muſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Might ſomething hope, but mid'ſt theſe times abuſe,</l>
               <l>To publiſh ought (of good) were to ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Gallants might ſomething minde (ſaue their ſpruce clothes</l>
               <l>Which were enough to damne theee, wherefore friend,</l>
               <l>Henceforth, or leaue to write, or hope, or ſend</l>
               <l>Thy Papers to the Counter, in whoſe Treaſure</l>
               <l>(Reſeru'd) our <hi>Brauers</hi> with more witte, more leiſure</l>
               <l>Hereafter may peruſe them, and extract</l>
               <l>This Morall from thy worke, that as the act</l>
               <l>Of vaine <hi>Ixyon Centaures</hi> got of Clowdes,</l>
               <l>So vapor infaire ſhewe, foule Monsters ſhrowdes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sanabimur ſi ſeparemur à Coetu.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>R. D. <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:4"/>
            <head>Ixyon.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>RAre's the Coniunction, the concorda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſwee</l>
               <l>When with endeuour, wit and <hi>Art</hi> do meet:</l>
               <l>When true <hi>Promethean</hi> fire doth warm the braine</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Induſtry</hi> lifts vp her high ſung ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Still ſoares, ſtill mounts (regardles of baſe things)</l>
               <l>As high as <hi>Fame</hi> doth on her golden Wings:</l>
               <l>But out alas, <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> refuſe</l>
               <l>To ſhead their influence on my ruder <hi>Muſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor could ſhe euer ſweetly moue her wing,</l>
               <l>Only as <hi>Carters</hi> whiſtle, ſo I ſing.</l>
               <l>They (to delight themſelues) do rudely chaunt,</l>
               <l>And that I pleaſe my ſelfe, I onely vaunt.</l>
               <l>For in all actions, mans delight him drawes,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Appetite</hi> is ſenſleſſe of all <hi>Lawes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then mount low verſe, to ſing <hi>Ixyons</hi> Fate,</l>
               <l>And to thy helpe, the <hi>Muſes</hi> inuocate.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:5"/>
               <l>Yee ſacred <hi>Deities,</hi> you I implore,</l>
               <l>Whom ſage <hi>Memoria</hi> bred, and nurſt of yore:</l>
               <l>Lend your aſſiſtance to my feeble ſcull,</l>
               <l>With your <hi>Pierean</hi> vigor make me full.</l>
               <l>Yee glorious Siſters of <hi>Parnaſſu</hi> hill,</l>
               <l>Your holie furie into mee diſtill.</l>
               <l>You, the <hi>Pegaſian</hi> Fount that daily haunt,</l>
               <l>And on the brimme do moſt diuinely chaunt:</l>
               <l>Now ſend your Influence, and mee inſpire,</l>
               <l>Highly to ſing the Iuſtice of your Sire.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon,</hi> (ſometime) the <hi>Theſſalian</hi> King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe high <hi>Ambition</hi> flewe on horrid wing:</l>
               <l>And checkt each vertuous motion that did riſe,</l>
               <l>To intercept (his bloodie enterpriſe)</l>
               <l>Soone after hee his marriage rites had done,</l>
               <l>And quite diſſolu'd his wiues white virgin Zone.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:5"/>
               <l>Thinkes with himſelfe, that well it might agree,</l>
               <l>To keepe the fruit, and yet to burne the Tree:</l>
               <l>The ſaples truncke bore on his withered top,</l>
               <l>A ſparkling <hi>Dyadem,</hi> a golden crop.</l>
               <l>Which to poſſeſſe, <hi>Ixyon</hi> ſtrange plots laies,</l>
               <l>(Longing to guild his browes with borrowed raies)</l>
               <l>The Crowne he aimes at (ſenſeles of remorſe,)</l>
               <l>Not by the Ladders helpe, but axes force.</l>
               <l>Nor will he by <hi>Succeſſion</hi> hope to clime,</l>
               <l>Nor reſt content the <hi>fruits</hi> maturing <hi>time.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ceaze it ſtrait (regardles of all right)</l>
               <l>Will is pure Iuſtice when it ſpeake from might.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eyoneus</hi> (that as a barre did ſtand,</l>
               <l>T' <hi>Ixyons</hi> hopes) muſt by ſome polliticke hand</l>
               <l>Be ſnatch't away, <hi>Ixyon</hi> plots the meanes,</l>
               <l>His thoughts are <hi>actors</hi> in moſt tragicke <hi>Sceanes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now his <hi>Genius</hi> prompteth him to <hi>warre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On ſome forg'd cauſe to moue a publicke Iarre.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:6"/>
               <l>To enter King <hi>Eyoneus</hi> fertill <hi>Land</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With warlike troopes, and with an armed band.</l>
               <l>With horſes hooues to furrow vp the plaine,</l>
               <l>And ſow the field with blood, in ſteed of Graine.</l>
               <l>On this waites danger, his cloſe hope replies:</l>
               <l>So this plot quickly borne, as quickly dies.</l>
               <l>And (like the flower of flax that fades i'th wombe)</l>
               <l>This proiectes birth is now become it's tombe.</l>
               <l>Becauſe (quoth he) his daughter is my wife,</l>
               <l>T'would blaſt my <hi>Fame,</hi> if I ſhould ſeeke his life</l>
               <l>By open Armes, therefore (how'ere I worke)</l>
               <l>This is no courſe, my hate muſt cloſely lurke.</l>
               <l>And t'were prepoſterous to waſt his land,</l>
               <l>Whoſe perſon now is (dreadles) in my hand.</l>
               <l>Beſides, I thinke this <hi>Axiom</hi> not vaine,</l>
               <l>"They that get much by blood, but little gaine.</l>
               <l>Theſe thoughts (intruding thus) doe yet want might</l>
               <l>For to extinguiſh his ſtill growing ſpight:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:6"/>
               <l>But new inuentions from his braine do flow,</l>
               <l>As faſt as <hi>Iuy</hi> ſprouts, or <hi>Muſhromps</hi> grow.</l>
               <l>Reſtles <hi>Ambition,</hi> whether do'ſt thou tend,</l>
               <l>Thy ſtill freſh <hi>Labours?</hi> to what horred end dread?</l>
               <l>Fraught'ſt thou <hi>Ixyons</hi> euer-working head,</l>
               <l>With nought but thoughts of <hi>horror,</hi> blood, and</l>
               <l>Hee's now thy Slaue, obaies thee at each nod,</l>
               <l>And thou (foule feend) art now become his God.</l>
               <l>Lead on bleſt <hi>Saint</hi> (ſaith he) and ſtill direct mee,</l>
               <l>While thus with richeſt <hi>Epethites</hi> I decke thee.</l>
               <l>Then as ſome <hi>Rymesters</hi> of theſe latter daies,</l>
               <l>Bedawbe blacke <hi>Dowdes</hi> with brighteſt Angels praiſe</l>
               <l>Swearing the <hi>Graces</hi> dwell within their cie,</l>
               <l>And that each part is ſome pure Deitie:</l>
               <l>So gins <hi>Ixyon</hi> to extoll his <hi>Saint,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with rich colours this blacke peece to paint.</l>
               <l>Thou art (quoth he) th'incyter to great deeds,</l>
               <l>For by thy only breath our <hi>honour</hi> breeds.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:7"/>
               <l>Thou only doeſt diſtinguiſh man from beaſt</l>
               <l>And lift'ſt whom thou poſſeſt boue the reſt:</l>
               <l>Thou tak'ſt from vs that <hi>Elementall earth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> with th'other three mixt ere our <hi>Birth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in that roome freſh ayre thou do'ſt infuſe</l>
               <l>Which makes vs mount aboue the ſprightly Muſe</l>
               <l>Thou art indeed that ſelfe-ſame louing fire,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtealth infuſed in the Gods ſuch Ire</l>
               <l>Againſt <hi>Promethius:</hi> burne cleere bright flame,</l>
               <l>To adde another title to my <hi>Name:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A ſingle ſcepter cannot poize my hand,</l>
               <l>But I'le ioyne <hi>Thrace</hi> vnto my natiue Land.</l>
               <l>Then warme my braine with thy caeleſtiall fire,</l>
               <l>For till my ſtarres eclipſe me I'le aſpire,</l>
               <l>Vſher mine actions, ſtill make good my hate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eyoneus</hi> graue mounts me to beſt of fate.</l>
               <l>By this the Sunne (eclip'ſt with duſt and ſweate,</l>
               <l>B'gan in the Sea to quench his thirſtie heate.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:7"/>
               <l>By this <hi>Apollo</hi> with deſcending beames,</l>
               <l>Began to pierce the ſiluer ſliding ſtreames:</l>
               <l>And (though halfe tir'de with trauaile) ſprightly ran,</l>
               <l>To drench his treſſes in the <hi>Ocean.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now that the fierie <hi>Plannet, God</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had t'ane his beames hence, and giu'n place to <hi>Night</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Night</hi> with broad ſable wings did fan the <hi>Sea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Taking her rice from off the watry <hi>Lea.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in her pitchie mantle ſittes on hie,</l>
               <l>Naild with a thouſand <hi>Starres</hi> vpon the <hi>skie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now ſhine <hi>Oryon</hi> and the <hi>Pleiades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes doe guild th' <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Cynthia</hi> in long diſheueld haire,</l>
               <l>With ſiluer <hi>Creſſent</hi> doth adorne her <hi>Spheare:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now toile-diſſoluing <hi>Night</hi> with ſilent charmes</l>
               <l>Welcome's <hi>Ixyon</hi> in her ſable armes.</l>
               <l>Dull <hi>Icelon</hi> hangs on their eyes like Lead,</l>
               <l>And ſummons all the family to bed.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:8"/>
               <l>Where all enioy ſweet, pleaſant downy reſt,</l>
               <l>Except <hi>Ixyon</hi> whoſe ſtill-troubled breſt,</l>
               <l>Cannot admit of wit-refreſhing ſleepe,</l>
               <l>But with his murtherous thoughts ſtrickt watch doth keepe.</l>
               <l>Yet (not forgetting <hi>Hymencall rights,</hi> harme,</l>
               <l>He hugges his wife with fained appetite. warme:</l>
               <l>Shee gentle Queene, pure, dreadles of all</l>
               <l>With her ſoft twines his hate child blood doth</l>
               <l>And feaſts him with rare Iunkets and ſuch ſweetes</l>
               <l>In whoſe fruition all delights doe meete. caſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> ſoone, her, and himſelfe doth pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Which done, ſhe ſleeps, <hi>Delights</hi> o'retane by</l>
               <l>Me thinkes the fruit yeelding ſuch pleaſant taſt</l>
               <l>Such liuely ſweets that yet vnperiſh't laſt,</l>
               <l>Might well extinguiſh that ſame blood-fed flame,</l>
               <l>That i'th trees duſt inter's the <hi>fellers fame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But nought preuailes, <hi>Eyoneus</hi> needs muſt fall,</l>
               <l>"No ſweetes can ſweeten a corrupted <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:8"/>
               <l>For now I heare <hi>Ixyon</hi> thanke his <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For meanes how to produce th'ffects of <hi>Hate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which <hi>Night</hi> (wel ſuting <hi>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  </hi> his blacker (thought)</l>
               <l>Into his minde hath firme, yet quickly brought:</l>
               <l>And now he ſpends the remnant of the <hi>Night</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Onely in wiſhing for th'approaching <hi>Light:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet he with <hi>horror</hi> meanes to cloud the day,</l>
               <l>Thirſtie <hi>Ambytion</hi> cannot brooke delay.</l>
               <l>And now <hi>Aurora</hi> with flow ſtately pace</l>
               <l>Diſtils her pearly drops on euery place.</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſeeing (vſher'd by that <hi>Starre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſtill conducts him to his burning <hi>Carre</hi>)</l>
               <l>Comes forth in ſtate, to take from earth againe</l>
               <l>What his Loue gaue, t'enrich each fertile plaine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> riſeth, and with quickeſt ſpeed,</l>
               <l>Sends to <hi>Ericthoe,</hi> whoſe dam'nd helpe he needs,</l>
               <l>Strickly commanding, that ſhe ſtraite puruay</l>
               <l>Some Hell-charm'd fogge to cannopie the
d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:9"/>
               <l>And by her a <hi>Sorcerie</hi> ſtorme to reare,</l>
               <l>Whoſe noyſe might make both men and Gods to feare:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ericthoe</hi> in a Caue of <hi>Theſſaly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That vnderpin'd a lofty promontorie</l>
               <l>Had her abiding, there no ſparke of <hi>Light,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did euer peepe, t'was there eternall <hi>Night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saue onely that ſome ſparkles did ariſe,</l>
               <l>From her halfe buried, euer-fiery eyes.</l>
               <l>Her hayreles ſcalpe was like a <hi>ſtatues</hi> head,</l>
               <l>Each ſide with a huge elſelocke furniſhed:</l>
               <l>Of colour like a blacke-roane horſes taile,</l>
               <l>All which a kercher of <hi>Bats</hi> wings doth vaile:</l>
               <l>Her facelike <hi>Mars,</hi> his front wrinkled with ire</l>
               <l>Or parchment leaues, late ſcorched by the fire:</l>
               <l>She once had teeth and lips, but truth to ſay,</l>
               <l>Time now hath worne, both teeth and lips away.</l>
               <l>Shee, scarnell backt, and hollow is her breſt,</l>
               <l>Her legges are crooked, and deform'd the reſt:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:9"/>
               <l>All parts with one another angrie bee,</l>
               <l>Onely her noſe and chinne doe ſtill agree,</l>
               <l>And (louingly) do alwayes kiſſe each other,</l>
               <l>Which her breath enuying with horrid ſmoother</l>
               <l>Seeks to diſioyne them, but yet (wanting might)</l>
               <l>Doth onely blaſt both, with her cruell ſpight,</l>
               <l>And makes them looke of ſuch a ſwartie red,</l>
               <l>As doth corrupted fleſh by <hi>Arte</hi> made dead:</l>
               <l>Thus liues <hi>Ericthoe,</hi> and by <hi>Sorcerie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth clogge the ſoule, with damn'd impietie.</l>
               <l>Hold gentle <hi>Muſe,</hi> do not thus looſely ſtray,</l>
               <l>But with high wing trace thy propoſed way:</l>
               <l>Now draw the Curtains, and vnmaske a deede</l>
               <l>May wonder-ſtrike the world, and humane ſeede.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> (hauing to <hi>Ericthoe</hi> ſent)</l>
               <l>Salutes <hi>Eyoneus with faire complement,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And him inuites, (the Morne yet being cleere)</l>
               <l>To hunt the ſauage Bore, or timerous Deere:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:10"/>
               <l>And after that, be pleaſed to acept</l>
               <l>A cuſtomarie thing the <hi>Auncients</hi> kept:</l>
               <l>Which was, that euery Sonne in <hi>Lawe</hi> did giue</l>
               <l>Gifts to his wiues <hi>Syre,</hi> and that vſe did liue</l>
               <l>Religiouſly obſeru'd through manie ages,</l>
               <l>Reuerenc't of all, confirm'd by <hi>learned Sages:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe gifts (when as their ſport is ended quite,</l>
               <l>And exerciſe hath ſharpned <hi>Appetite</hi>)</l>
               <l>He ſaith hee would preſent him at a <hi>Feaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where onely hee ſhould be his <hi>Princely Gueſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee condiſcends, ſo ride they to their ſport,</l>
               <l>And for Field-game, change the delights of <hi>Court.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scarce had the <hi>Deere</hi> bin rowzed by their hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</l>
               <l>(Whoſe noiſe with <hi>Ecchoes</hi> made the hils rebound)</l>
               <l>When blacke <hi>Ericthoe</hi> by her <hi>Sorcerie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had much diſtemperd the day-guiding <hi>Skie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It ſeemd that <hi>loue,</hi> (mou'd with ſom noiſe on earth</l>
               <l>To confound that, had giuen his <hi>Thunder</hi> breath.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:10"/>
               <l>For now it ſpake lowd (mixt with haile and raine)</l>
               <l>And Pallid <hi>Lightning</hi> blaſts the hopefull graine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Segeſtaes</hi> ſonne (bound by <hi>Ericthoes</hi> charme)</l>
               <l>Now cannot keepe the windes from doing harme,</l>
               <l>Nor yet confine them in their lowe-built Caue,</l>
               <l>But that for paſſage boy ſtrouſly they raue,</l>
               <l>Forcing their freedome, with as awfull power,</l>
               <l>As if they meant to teare their marble Tower:</l>
               <l>And as ſwift Currents, long reſtraind from vent,</l>
               <l>Grow rougher through their forc't impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</l>
               <l>And with the clamorous roaring that they make,</l>
               <l>Do force the Heards, the fertile Banks forſake:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the windes (ruſhing from forth their den)</l>
               <l>Bring ſudden terror, on amazed men:</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Turrets</hi> tremble, there huge <hi>Steeples</hi> ſhake,</l>
               <l>Some (ſtorm-torne) tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, moſt their place forſake</l>
               <l>Strange, ſtrong effects of a bad mixed potion,</l>
               <l>To giue things ſenſles, ſuch quick ſudden motion?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:11"/>
               <l>Coſt on faire buildings laide, was laide amiſſe,</l>
               <l>For what but now had forme, a <hi>Chaos</hi> is:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Coniurde Tempest, makes the Thickets nod, ſtorme</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Such helliſh power dwels in <hi>Ericthoes</hi> rod)</l>
               <l>Trees, whoſe ſtrength could not but oppoſe this</l>
               <l>By oppoſition looſe both life and forme:</l>
               <l>And they that bore their tops moſt high,</l>
               <l>Are now the meaneſt vnderneath the Skie.</l>
               <l>Nothing but Shrubs are ſafe, who low in State,</l>
               <l>Are not yet ripe for ſuch prepoſterous <hi>Fate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But yet <hi>Eyoneus,</hi> like a <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wrell</hi> bough</l>
               <l>(Vntouch't, ſaue with the <hi>horror</hi> of this ſhowe)</l>
               <l>Did cheerfullie aduance his reuerent head,</l>
               <l>Which in <hi>Ixyon</hi> moſt amazement bred:</l>
               <l>For on this <hi>Storme</hi> which tooke this ample ſcope,</l>
               <l>Stood the firme <hi>Baſes</hi> of his bloody hope.</l>
               <l>Whereon like a <hi>Colloſſus</hi> hee might ſtand,</l>
               <l>(By <hi>Murther</hi> propt) and gouerne either Land:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:11"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Murther</hi> hee thinks no <hi>Sinne,</hi> knowing few frowne</l>
               <l>On <hi>deeds</hi> (thogh nere ſo <hi>black,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts crown,</l>
               <l>And had <hi>Eyoneus</hi> here endurde the worſt,</l>
               <l>T'would haue ſeem'd accidentall that forc't,</l>
               <l>And had this <hi>Tempest</hi> ruinde him and all,</l>
               <l>What was inhumane, had ſeem'd <hi>naturall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Tempeſt (miſſing this intended wracke)</l>
               <l>Somewhat of her late force began to ſlacke,</l>
               <l>And in farre calmer termes her rage to ſpend,</l>
               <l>For now <hi>Ericthoes</hi> Charme tooke ſolemne end.</l>
               <l>And as a route of rude vntutor'd <hi>Hyndes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe beſt bad ſenſes, cauſeleſſe <hi>Furie</hi> blindes,</l>
               <l>In mad confuſed manner moue ſome <hi>Iarre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Making Trade-engines inſtruments of <hi>Warre</hi>)</l>
               <l>One beares an Axe, th'other a Hammer brings,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Fury</hi> can make weapons of any thing:</l>
               <l>And (weakely arm'd with ſwords) but ſtrong in <hi>Ire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conſume the Neighbour villages with <hi>Fire:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:12"/>
               <l>Knowing th'are <hi>Traytors,</hi> nought can them aſſwage</l>
               <l>But on all things, they execute their rage:</l>
               <l>Their liues being forfeit, aime at things moſt faire</l>
               <l>"He that for nought ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope, ſhuld noght diſpaire:</l>
               <l>Yet from the <hi>Prince,</hi> if ſome graue man be ſent,</l>
               <l>To promiſe pardon, if they be content</l>
               <l>To ceaſe their mutinie, and to ſubmit</l>
               <l>To him that weares the awfull <hi>Coronet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At firſt, a buſie murmur's only heard,</l>
               <l>As if ſome vnknowne <hi>Stratageme</hi> they fear'd,</l>
               <l>But (ſoone reſolu'd) their Armes they caſt away,</l>
               <l>And in moſt gratefull tearms proclaime their ioy.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the windes (freed from <hi>Ericthoes</hi> Charme)</l>
               <l>Seeme to repent their lately raſh done harme,</l>
               <l>And quietly (being manacled beneath)</l>
               <l>Doth only Fanne the <hi>World,</hi> with mildeſt breath:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Thunder</hi> huſht, and <hi>Ioues</hi> late fiery fumes</l>
               <l>Their proper <hi>Element</hi> do reaſſume.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:12"/>
               <l>The rayne's appeaſde, and <hi>Iunoes Nuntius</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is to the world ſeene as propitious,</l>
               <l>And in her ſeuerall colours richly dight,</l>
               <l>(Arching the <hi>Skie</hi>) doth promiſe purer <hi>Light.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> faines himſelfe with ioy orecome,</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>Eyoneus</hi> had eſcapt the ſtorme,</l>
               <l>And preſently conducts him, as to take</l>
               <l>Theſe Spowfall gifts, where he muſt all forſake,</l>
               <l>T'a <hi>Lodge,</hi> (for murther acted) thither goes,</l>
               <l>"A fained friend's worſe then ten open Foes.</l>
               <l>There come, and ſeated, Ceremonious rites</l>
               <l>Promiſe faire <hi>Welcome,</hi> ſeaſon'd with delights:</l>
               <l>When in deepe ſilence, full of expectation,</l>
               <l>Noting <hi>Ixyons</hi> formall Celebration,</l>
               <l>And ſeeming dutious zeale, <hi>Eyoneus</hi> Chaire,</l>
               <l>Gins to ſincke with him, to ſome lower ſtaire:</l>
               <l>Hee (dreadles) ſits, and preſently doth ſlippe,</l>
               <l>Through ſome fewe ſticks, into a fierie pitte:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:13"/>
               <l>Whoſe low, cloſe, ſeruent heate, and diſmall <hi>fume,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did in an inſtant, his liues ſtrength conſume.</l>
               <l>Slaues take him vp, but ere with him they riſe,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Soule</hi> (being better wing'd) was boue the <hi>Skies.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou moſt vnworthie, both of name &amp; being,</l>
               <l>How couldſt thou act this thy vniuſt decreeing,</l>
               <l>And vnder ſhewe of <hi>Loue</hi> (compos'd of durt)</l>
               <l>Kill, whom a <hi>helliſh</hi> ſtorme thought <hi>Sin</hi> to hurt?</l>
               <l>What breach of holie <hi>Hospitalitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of open kindnes, and <hi>Friends</hi> loyaltie,</l>
               <l>Haſt thou herein committed? Oh theſe ils</l>
               <l>Would put rough teeth, into the ſmootheſt quils:</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou giuen notice of thy hates condition,</l>
               <l>Or had it bene in <hi>Hostile oppoſition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leſſe had thy ſcandall bene, but with faire face</l>
               <l>To ſhrowde ſuch deeds, is as abhord, as baſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſſimulation!</hi> Oh, there's nothing worſe,</l>
               <l>Tis <hi>Treaſons</hi> mother, of all ills the Nurſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:13"/>
               <l>A falſe glaſſe to the <hi>Soule,</hi> that ſtill preſents</l>
               <l>Things in faire formes, nere crown'd with good euents:</l>
               <l>The fire that burnes giues warning by his flame</l>
               <l>T'auoide the ill his pointed <hi>angles</hi> frame,</l>
               <l>But that in aſhes rak't, vnfear'd, vnſeene,</l>
               <l>Is the moſt dangerous miniſter of ſpleene:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sea</hi> whom <hi>Aeolus</hi> doth moue to anger,</l>
               <l>Doth by ſome ſigne foretell the flowing danger:</l>
               <l>And all things that bode perill vnto man,</l>
               <l>Haue tokens that pregoe the hurt they can;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sunne</hi> (declining) tells vs t'wil be darke,</l>
               <l>And though ſome curre doe bite before he barke</l>
               <l>Yet in the ſpacious world was neuer found</l>
               <l>A dog that (fawning) ere was knowne to wound;</l>
               <l>But <hi>man</hi> that ſhould be beſt, is <hi>Lord</hi> of all,</l>
               <l>As <hi>goods,</hi> ſo <hi>vices</hi> to his ſhare do fall:</l>
               <l>For this (in knowing creatures) hath bene euer</l>
               <l>To ſee the beſt, yet in the worſt perſeuer.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:14"/>
               <l>Vaine men that <hi>Deifide</hi> themſelues, do deeme</l>
               <l>When <hi>Tytles</hi> timpanize them, then they ſeeme</l>
               <l>Like bladders puft, or like a ſtrutting <hi>Player</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(He dawb'd with kingly forme, they ſtuft with aire,)</l>
               <l>And (ſeuer'd from the multitude by name)</l>
               <l>Thinke they are bleſt with neuer dying <hi>Fame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Fame</hi> (though nere ſo worthily atchieu'd)</l>
               <l>We ſee is or abortiue, or ſhort liu'd,</l>
               <l>And vnto no man any comforts brings,</l>
               <l>But flies aboue vs with inconſtant wings.</l>
               <l>Oh why did not the <hi>Heauens</hi> by graue foreſight</l>
               <l>Ad to the windes ſtrength their reuenging might</l>
               <l>To ceaze <hi>Ixyon?</hi> but they are content</l>
               <l>By ſparing to increaſe his puniſhment:</l>
               <l>And ſcourge him when he is in greateſt ſtate,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Vengeance</hi> is full growne, falles in height of <hi>Fate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> (ſtain'd with the rich blood he ſpilt)</l>
               <l>Vntouch't in euery place, ſaue with his guilt,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:14"/>
               <l>Wiſheth his <hi>Sences</hi> had not muffled bin,</l>
               <l>To lead him blindfold to ſo foule a ſin:</l>
               <l>And that <hi>Eyoneus</hi> death had bene preuented,</l>
               <l>Which as t'was quickly done, was ſoone repented:</l>
               <l>Curſeth his <hi>Fate,</hi> and in repentant ſort</l>
               <l>Conuaies <hi>Eyoneus</hi> breathles corpes to <hi>Court:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where when he came, the care-bethronged <hi>Queene</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Soone as her <hi>father</hi> liueleſſe ſhe had ſeene,</l>
               <l>Ask't whoſe blacke deed that was, <hi>Ixyon</hi> ſtrait</l>
               <l>(Weeping) acknowledged t'was his <hi>deceit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And what he cloſely acted, did reueale,</l>
               <l>"(Murther's <hi>a Sinne</hi> no <hi>Conſcience</hi> can conceale)</l>
               <l>Which very words extinguiſh't her liues fire,</l>
               <l>For at the ſound thereof ſhe did expire.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time,</hi> that with ſharpeſt Sithe, and purple wings</l>
               <l>In his ſwift race to <hi>Diſſolution</hi> brings</l>
               <l>The great'ſt and worthieſt monuments on <hi>earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe end is dateles, like his vnknowne birth,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:15"/>
               <l>Hath now with <hi>Fate</hi> ſo leagueally agreed,</l>
               <l>As in <hi>Ixyon</hi> diſcontent to breed,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Conſcience</hi> is his ſcourge, he feeles thereby</l>
               <l>A ſmarting fence of his impiety:</l>
               <l>The funerall tapers that adorn'd their herſe</l>
               <l>Shall giue ſafe conduct to my mournfull <hi>verſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which (not extinct with ſighes) did cleerly burne</l>
               <l>Ouer their two-fold, timeleſſe, filled <hi>Vrne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vntill the lateſt obſequies were done,</l>
               <l>And they both laid vnder one marble ſtone.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyons</hi> cleerer iudgement then exhalde</l>
               <l>Thoſe miſts of <hi>horror</hi> which his <hi>Sences</hi> vailde:</l>
               <l>And gaue him leaue to looke into his <hi>Soule,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which (charg'd with great accounts) did ſtrait controule</l>
               <l>All his delights on earth, they being fled,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hop</hi> keepes him liuing, <hi>Paſſion</hi> ſtrikes him dead:</l>
               <l>And both together with their ſeuerall darts,</l>
               <l>Wound and torment all his interior parts:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:15"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hope</hi> bids him liue, and cancell <hi>care</hi> at length,</l>
               <l>But in meane time his <hi>Care</hi> conſumes his ſtrength</l>
               <l>Vnmarroweth his bones, vnſappes his vaines,</l>
               <l>And keepes him full of diſagreeing paines:</l>
               <l>And thus he liues in deepeſt paſſions drown'd,</l>
               <l>His preſent griefes all future Ioyes confound:</l>
               <l>All men abhorre him for his ill vrg'd gall,</l>
               <l>"He is moſt wretched, none lament at all.</l>
               <l>And thus (accompanied by none but <hi>griefe</hi>)</l>
               <l>He leaues his kingdome like a midnight thiefe,</l>
               <l>And like a wanderer ſtraies about the earth,</l>
               <l>Curſing his <hi>Fate,</hi> exclaiming on his birth:</l>
               <l>Wiſhing that day wherein he firſt drew breath</l>
               <l>Had by his funerall proclaim'd his death,</l>
               <l>That when he crept out of his mothers wombe</l>
               <l>H'had (wailed) gon into his lateſt <hi>Tombe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then a ſullen ſilence in him breeds</l>
               <l>He only with his teares his ſorrow feeds:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:16"/>
               <l>Still they diſtill apace yet are not don,</l>
               <l>His eyes are ſprings that neuer ceaſe to run:</l>
               <l>One drop, anothers roome doth ſtrait ſupplie,</l>
               <l>Yet nere exhauſt's the current of his eye:</l>
               <l>At laſt his <hi>griefe</hi> with <hi>care</hi> his breſt o're-fraughts,</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (tirde with thinking thus, he vents his thoughts:</l>
               <l>Furrow my cheekes ſalt teares, plow vp your way,</l>
               <l>You are a tribute that mine eyes muſt pay:</l>
               <l>In time the deaw of <hi>Heauen</hi> doth pierce the flint,</l>
               <l>And you ſhould run till you haue made a dint</l>
               <l>On either cheeke, nor then ſhould take your reſt</l>
               <l>But with moiſt offerings keepe them ſtill poſſeſt:</l>
               <l>You did direct me in my crueltie,</l>
               <l>Therefore I'le drowne you both vntill you die:</l>
               <l>Which ſince my teares (your naturall rhewme) refuſe</l>
               <l>Deepe ſighes Ile make tempeſtuous to that vſe,</l>
               <l>The which ſhall neuer ceaſe till you they wracke,</l>
               <l>But moue rough billows on my teares ſmooth backe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:16"/>
               <l>But whence proceeds this childiſh idle flood?</l>
               <l>Whence? from laſting crime of ſhedding blood:</l>
               <l>Which to wipe off, I ſtriue with as vaine hope</l>
               <l>As they that hourely waſh an <hi>Aethiope:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor all the <hi>Scas</hi> i'th world (though on me ſpilt)</l>
               <l>Yet could not clenſe me of his leapours guilt:</l>
               <l>Then why do theſe ſlight drops fall from mine eie?</l>
               <l>To feede my griefes Lamps that would elſe be drie:</l>
               <l>Oh that <hi>contrition,</hi> offerings, or theſe teares</l>
               <l>(Selfe conquering trophies which my ſorrow beares)</l>
               <l>Or all that is, or may deuiſed bee,</l>
               <l>To make a guiltie <hi>Soule</hi> with peace agree,</l>
               <l>Could but redeeme the <hi>Glory</hi> I haue loſt,</l>
               <l>How would my <hi>Soule</hi> (though euer weeping) boaſt?</l>
               <l>But none of theſe can e're inter my ſhame,</l>
               <l>(Now King) of nothing but a large defame</l>
               <l>Which will liue euer, and wax huger ſtill,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Report</hi> doth (going) growe of good or ill:)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:17"/>
               <l>Nor ſet me in my priſtine <hi>Innocence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"There is no ſting like that of <hi>Conſcience:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet theſe (though bootles) here I vow to ſpend,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Time</hi> conſpire with <hi>Fate</hi> to worke mine end.</l>
               <l>Theſe and the like from a vaſt <hi>Sea</hi> of woes</l>
               <l>That in <hi>Ixyons</hi> guiltie breſt ſtill flowes</l>
               <l>He ſtill repeates, and careleſly doth ſtray,</l>
               <l>"He that is poore, is ne're out of his way:</l>
               <l>At laſt with wearie limbes, and bared ſealpe</l>
               <l>He in's progreſſion mounts the frozen <hi>Alpes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And (by <hi>diſpaire</hi>) almoſt to madnes drouen</l>
               <l>His long neglected hands he reares to <hi>Heauen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And (wanting meanes for other ſacrifice)</l>
               <l>Thus on his knees beſpake the <hi>Deities:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yee ſtill-agreeing powers, emptie of <hi>Iarres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That in your daily motion tread on <hi>Starres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You that o're looke this our terreſtriall <hi>Ball,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe influence giues forme and life to all,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:17"/>
               <l>You that in <hi>Characters,</hi> ſubſcrib'de by <hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Record the worlds vaſt frame, and vtmoſt date,</l>
               <l>Oh let a mortalls prayers, and teares intreate</l>
               <l>Safe paſſe for ſome fewe words, to <hi>Ioues</hi> high ſeate,</l>
               <l>And when (clad all in ayre) they mount on high,</l>
               <l>Be pleas'd dread powers, to let them pierce the <hi>skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great ſonne of <hi>Saturne,</hi> euerliuing <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By whoſe permiſſion euery thing doth moue,</l>
               <l>Eternall eſſence that with awfull mace</l>
               <l>Doeſt rule all things in <hi>Heauen,</hi> and humane race,</l>
               <l>Whoſe onely ſmile can ſaue, or frowne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>Whoſe very breath doth make the <hi>Ocean</hi> boyle,</l>
               <l>Whoſe euery action filles the world with wonder</l>
               <l>Whoſe eies dart <hi>Lightning,</hi> &amp; whoſe voice is
<hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe glorious <hi>Throne</hi> the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> vnderbaries</l>
               <l>That out-ſhin'ſt all, clad in thy roabe of
<hi>Starr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:18"/>
               <l>Oh if a man, whoſe guilt ſpeakes in his face,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe <hi>Sins</hi> exclude from all good hope of grace</l>
               <l>May dare attempt, with blood-polluted hands</l>
               <l>To touch thy Pedeſtell, whereon there ſtands</l>
               <l>VVrought by diuine <hi>Art,</hi> ſuch a world of <hi>Glory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As to all worlds ſhall be an ample ſtory:</l>
               <l>Then et <hi>Ixyon</hi> (rich in nought but ſhame,</l>
               <l>And all the adiuncts to a vaſt defame)</l>
               <l>VVith teares petitionarie thee deſire,</l>
               <l>To purge his <hi>Sins</hi> with thine immortall fire,</l>
               <l>Clenſe what's corrupt, make pure what is moſt fowle</l>
               <l>And of my ſpeckled, make a glorious <hi>Soule:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The more my <hi>Sin,</hi> the greater is thy <hi>Fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou do purge it with thy hallowed flame:</l>
               <l>VVill not you chriſtall ſtellified gate</l>
               <l>Ope, and with milde aſpect adorne my <hi>Fate?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:18"/>
               <l>Heare me dread <hi>Ioue,</hi> or if thou wilt not heare,</l>
               <l>Yet take ſome notice of theſe penitent teares,</l>
               <l>Could my tongue ſpeak as loud as doth my <hi>Sinne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With my ſhril praiers ere now, th'adſt rowzed bin:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill ile pray, and with my diſmall cries,</l>
               <l>Fan ope thy <hi>Glories</hi> Curtaine, the blew <hi>Skies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And till my ſinnes with mercie be commixt,</l>
               <l>A kneeling liuing <hi>Statue</hi> here be fixt.</l>
               <l>At this th'appeaſed <hi>Heauens</hi> began to ſmile,</l>
               <l>And this great <hi>Deitie</hi> that had all this while</l>
               <l>With an attentiue care obſeru'd the prayers</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> ſpent, his penitence and teares:</l>
               <l>(Prompted by pittie) doth reſolue once more</l>
               <l>To make <hi>Ixyon</hi> happier then before:</l>
               <l>And for his kingdomes loſſe, hee meanes to giue</l>
               <l>A place of reſidence, where hee ſhall liue.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:19"/>
               <l>Mating himſelfe (aboue i'th arched <hi>Skie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There ſporting with the <hi>Gods</hi> eternallie:)</l>
               <l>To this great worke, hee ſummons inſtantly</l>
               <l>His <hi>Sonne,</hi> and <hi>Herald</hi> (winged <hi>Mercury</hi>)</l>
               <l>With his gold <hi>plumes</hi> throgh th'aire to make quick flight,</l>
               <l>And be a welcome <hi>Nuntius</hi> to this wight:</l>
               <l>Inioyning <hi>Hermes</hi> on the <hi>Alpes</hi> t'appeare,</l>
               <l>(From whence <hi>Ixyons</hi> prayer pierc't his care)</l>
               <l>And whom he found there (weeping in <hi>Dispaire</hi>)</l>
               <l>To Vſher him through the yeelding <hi>aire:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhat needed more to him of <hi>wit</hi> that's <hi>God?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To'th wiſe one word's enough, to him <hi>Ioues</hi> nod:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hermes</hi> with ſpeed quicker then thought of mind</l>
               <l>Lights on the <hi>Alpes,</hi> as was by <hi>Ioue</hi> aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>And there (with hands vpreard) <hi>Ixyon</hi> found</l>
               <l>Kneeling, his knees euen growne vnto the ground:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:19"/>
               <l>VVho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (when he ſees) he with his <hi>rod</hi> him charmes,</l>
               <l>Bids him be dreadleſſe of all future harmes,</l>
               <l>And fro the cold earth (moyſtned with his teares)</l>
               <l>To riſe and follow him emptie of feares:</l>
               <l>(VVhich ſaid) through th'aire his ſiluer <hi>Rod</hi> hee moues,</l>
               <l>And executed ſo the will of <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> now aboue in <hi>Heauen</hi> is plac't,</l>
               <l>VVelcom'd by <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and by him grac't,</l>
               <l>And now <hi>Ixyon</hi> would my <hi>Muſe</hi> might leaue thee,</l>
               <l>But of that hope, thy worſt <hi>Fate</hi> doth bereaue me:</l>
               <l>Hadſt bene contented when thou wert ſo bleſt</l>
               <l>Th'adſt ſtill bene happie, and my <hi>Muſe</hi> tane reſt:</l>
               <l>But thy <hi>Ambition</hi> cauſde thy ſo great fall,</l>
               <l>And that of all ills is originall.</l>
               <l>But why taxe I thee for ſuch loſſe of <hi>glory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That dare with ſo young <hi>Muſe</hi> attempt thy ſtory?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:20"/>
               <l>I ſhould haue left it to ſome learned Pen</l>
               <l>That had bene deeply ſteept in <hi>Hippochrene:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As thou in thy attempt, I muſt fall too,</l>
               <l>Though my fall cannot be ſo great, and low:</l>
               <l>Yet were my ruine iuſt as neere as thine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis honour t'haue attempted things diuine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then on my <hi>Muſe</hi> in this thy forward race,</l>
               <l>Vſher thy ſeruant with thy beſt of grace</l>
               <l>To end this little worke, and heere I ſweare</l>
               <l>Some worthie <hi>Trophie</hi> to thy name Ile reare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyon</hi> (ſeated thus by <hi>Ioues</hi> conſent)</l>
               <l>Saw thoſe moſt enuyed were moſt eminent,</l>
               <l>For his great height did in ſome <hi>Gods</hi> infuſe</l>
               <l>A kinde of <hi>hate,</hi> which yet they durſt not vſe:</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Icelon,</hi> cauſe from him hee extorted</l>
               <l>Much time, which he with ſo blacke thoghts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:20"/>
               <l>Next <hi>Aeolus,</hi> for by a Witches rod</l>
               <l>H'had made him ſeeme a <hi>Tyrant</hi> and no <hi>God:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hymen</hi> was alſo ſwolne with much deſpight,</l>
               <l>Becauſe his holy <hi>Lawes</hi> he ſo did ſlight:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhamnuſia</hi> inly vext, and much did rue,</l>
               <l>Becauſe her puniſhment, which was his due</l>
               <l>Was not (as yet) inflicted on his head,</l>
               <l>That was by <hi>Vice</hi> into ſuch horror led:</l>
               <l>In others (too) much ſpleen which knowne to <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee with his frowne doth checke, and ſo remoue.</l>
               <l>Thus by the <hi>Gods,</hi> finding this ſweete reliefe,</l>
               <l>Purg'd of his Crime, as alſo of the griefe</l>
               <l>His Crime brought on him, he begins to ſwell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mans</hi> higheſt rice is neereſt ſteppe to <hi>Hell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For now <hi>Ixyon</hi> doth reteine no ſence</l>
               <l>Of his late guilt, or ſting of <hi>Conſcience:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:21"/>
               <l>But as a <hi>Letcher</hi> in the <hi>Surgions</hi> cure,</l>
               <l>Vowes (if once well) to be no more impure,</l>
               <l>And ſweares hee'le neuer clippe his <hi>Whore</hi> againe,</l>
               <l>(And meanes ſo too, as long as hee feeles paine)</l>
               <l>Yet is no ſooner cured of his harmes,</l>
               <l>But hee ſtrait leapes into his <hi>Harlot,</hi> armes:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo <hi>Ixyon</hi> (purged from this ſin)</l>
               <l>To attempt a greater farre doth thus begin:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioues</hi> wife and Siſter, whether by her eye</l>
               <l>Or by the power of <hi>Cupids</hi> Deitie,</l>
               <l>I'le not diſtinguiſh, ſtrooke him ſo in loue,</l>
               <l>As to <hi>Heauens Queene,</hi> his <hi>Luſt</hi>-ſuite hee durſt moue:</l>
               <l>And (warm'd with much more then <hi>Promethea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> fire)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuno</hi> hee courts to ſate his leaud deſire:</l>
               <l>Oh the vnbounded <hi>Lust,</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That in their bloods height no one reaſon ſcan,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:21"/>
               <l>But abuſe fauours that haue them rewarded,</l>
               <l>Nor p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritie of <hi>States</hi> is then regarded,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princes</hi> neglected, nay the <hi>Gods</hi> profan'de</l>
               <l>To get a pleaſure loſt, e're fully gain'd:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Reaſons</hi> light, cleere as the lampe of day,</l>
               <l>Shines in each Roome of this our houſe of clay,</l>
               <l>Saue thoſe that ſerue our luſt, and they are left,</l>
               <l>Of all but ſenſuall appetite bereft:</l>
               <l>No light ſhines there, and <hi>Poets</hi> workes importune,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Luſt</hi> makes vs more blind then they faine <hi>fortune</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ixyons</hi> heate keepes him from being mute,</l>
               <l>And prompts him thus to moue his loathed ſute:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Immortall greatnes, Deitie</hi> moſt pure,</l>
               <l>Whoſe name, and glory euer ſhall endure:</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to what I here preſent in feare,</l>
               <l>To lend a willing, and a gratious care:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:22"/>
               <l>Nor let my boldnes any anger moue,</l>
               <l>Since faults are no faults, that are done by <hi>Loue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From ſtile of all preſumption, that doth free</l>
               <l>My great attempt, my ſuite, my name and mee:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Gods</hi> haue lai'd aſide their great eſtate,</l>
               <l>To court faire <hi>Shepheardeſſes, Loue</hi> and <hi>Fate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are aboue all, <hi>Loue</hi> raignes in euery part,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> (clad in armes) was wounded by his dart:</l>
               <l>And as his power can take from <hi>Gods,</hi> euen ſo</l>
               <l>It can adde worth to vs that are belowe:</l>
               <l>Then by this rule <hi>I'me</hi> worthy of thy <hi>Loue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made great by that which hath abaſed <hi>Ioue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which let me but poſſeſſe (perfections <hi>Queene</hi>)</l>
               <l>And I'le be dreadles of your husbands ſpleene:</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall his <hi>Cyclops</hi> in me poſſions moue,</l>
               <l>"The flames of <hi>Aetna</hi> match not thoſe of <hi>Loue:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:22"/>
               <l>And neuer ſhame with me to act <hi>Loues</hi> deed,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Gods</hi> haue often mixt with humane ſeed.</l>
               <l>At this th'incenſed <hi>Queene,</hi> whoſe ſiluer brow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beautie</hi> and <hi>Dread</hi> (in ſeuerall formes) did ſhow:</l>
               <l>In an amazed maieſtie thought good,</l>
               <l>To cure with <hi>Vengeance</hi> this diſeaſe a'th blood:</l>
               <l>Yet knowing in <hi>Ioues</hi> thoughts he ſat ſo high,</l>
               <l>Omitt's reuenge, and makes this ſharpe reply:</l>
               <l>And is this then the tribute that you pay,</l>
               <l>To him breath'd <hi>Heauenly</hi> fire in earthly clay?</l>
               <l>Are theſe the offerings due vnto his ſhrine,</l>
               <l>That did thy clew of miſerie vntwine,</l>
               <l>And when <hi>Diſpaire</hi> ſat heauie on thy breſt</l>
               <l>Remou'd thy torments, gaue thy ſorrowes reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Hath then great <hi>Ioue,</hi> (my dreaded Lord and brother</l>
               <l>In pardoning one ſin, thus produc't another?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:23"/>
               <l>This then I ſee for truth ſhall ſtill endure,</l>
               <l>'Pittie in <hi>Gods</hi> makes men to ſinne ſecure:</l>
               <l>I'le anſwere thee as once <hi>Latena</hi> did,</l>
               <l>Her nightly wandering daughter, that vnhid</l>
               <l>Doth with her virgin body <hi>Lampe</hi> darke night,</l>
               <l>Once grieu'd to be ſo ſeene to humane ſight,</l>
               <l>She of her mother preſently requeſted</l>
               <l>To be with ſome rich proper roabe inueſted,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe might euer weare to hide her ſhame,</l>
               <l>Preſerue her modeſtie, and ſecure her fame:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Latona</hi> wiſely anſwered againe,</l>
               <l>That thy requeſt is idle, fond and vaine;</l>
               <l>For ſometime th'art ſo big, no robe can hide thee,</l>
               <l>Sometime ſo little, we can ſcarce eſpie thee:</l>
               <l>Then ſince thou art ſo ſubiect vnto change,</l>
               <l>Thou 'bout the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> ſtill ſhalt naked range:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:23"/>
               <l>And that's the cauſe <hi>Luna</hi> abhorres the light,</l>
               <l>And ne're is ſeene to vs but in the <hi>Night:</hi>)</l>
               <l>Thou (more then ſhe her forme) do'ſt change thy minde,</l>
               <l>Thy vaſt deſires are in no bounds confin'de:</l>
               <l>Sometime thy thoughts are humble as the earth</l>
               <l>Which thou wert made of, and which gaue thee birth,</l>
               <l>Sometime (as now) thou do'ſt as vainly ſwell,</l>
               <l>As he that for his pride was caſt to <hi>Hell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then what one thing can fit thy diſpoſition,</l>
               <l>That's of ſo ſtrange and various a condition?</l>
               <l>From thy abhorred <hi>Luſt</hi> I will be free,</l>
               <l>As ſhe her daughter, ſo I'le anſwere thee:</l>
               <l>Which is immoueable, ceaſe to diſpute,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> could get no gowne, nor thou thy ſuite.</l>
               <l>Yet (ſaith <hi>Ixyon</hi>) heare me e're you go,</l>
               <l>Let not cold chaſtitie benumne you ſo:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:24"/>
               <l>As to contemne my loue, be my Loues mate,</l>
               <l>Though not to crowne my loue, to quite your hate:</l>
               <l>'le not deſiſt for this your firſt reply,</l>
               <l>Who (faintly) craues, inſtructeth to denie:</l>
               <l>Know mightie <hi>Queene, Ioue</hi> doth you ſo much wrong,</l>
               <l>As y'are not iuſt, if you <hi>Reuenge</hi> prolong:</l>
               <l>Changing himſelfe into a golden ſhower</l>
               <l>He did force ope <hi>Acriſius</hi> brazen tower</l>
               <l>To enioy <hi>Danae,</hi> and on her begot,</l>
               <l>One that by's valour did race out the blot</l>
               <l>His baſtard birth brought on him, like a <hi>Bull,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He with <hi>Europa</hi> made his pleaſure full:</l>
               <l>In a <hi>Swans</hi> ſhape, on <hi>Laeda</hi> he begot</l>
               <l>Two, two-fold eggs, in one of which were ſhut</l>
               <l>The fatall ſparkes that ſet the brand on fire,</l>
               <l>Which in <hi>Troyes</hi> raines did to'th clouds aſpire:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:24"/>
               <l>Theſe are the meaneſt of his luſtfull Scapes,</l>
               <l>Made monſtrous by the many ſeuerall <hi>Rapes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He hath beſides committed, and can you then</l>
               <l>Be leſſe vindictiue then we ſilly men?</l>
               <l>Our blood mixt with our gall, doth inly boyle,</l>
               <l>To act reuenge we doe refuſe no toyle:</l>
               <l>But to all dangers do our liues expoſe,</l>
               <l>Of priuate <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and of publike foes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delight</hi> ſhall vſher yours (renowned <hi>Queene</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleaſure</hi> ſhall crowne Reuenge, and ſweeten ſpleene:</l>
               <l>That with your ſelfe you ſhall diſpute at leiſure,</l>
               <l>Whether were ſweeteſt, your reuenge, or pleaſure.</l>
               <l>Know ſelfe-abuſing man (<hi>Iuno</hi> replies)</l>
               <l>Thou art too baſe to mixe with <hi>Deities:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet wert thou each way worthy of my <hi>Loue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or could there be a greater power then <hi>Ioue?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:25"/>
               <l>With notes more ſweet then muſick of the <hi>Spheares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To charme my <hi>Sences,</hi> or delight mine eares:</l>
               <l>All ſhould not moue me, loyall I'le remaine,</l>
               <l>"Vnlawfull pleaſure, brings a lawfull paine:</l>
               <l>Thou that do'ſt ſugar poiſon, and do'ſt ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reuenge</hi> is pleaſant, there will come a day</l>
               <l>When with bedewed cheeks thy ſelfe ſhalt tell,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Reuenge</hi> on earth, buies a Reuenge in <hi>Hell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Ioues</hi> dread will, my thoughts ſhall neuer ſtart,</l>
               <l>"Reuenge is <hi>treaſon</hi> in a ſubiects hart:</l>
               <l>I am his Subiect, ſo more <hi>Honour</hi> lies</l>
               <l>In bearings wrongs, then quitting iniuries.</l>
               <l>Which ſaid, with ſtately ſpeed from him ſhe moues,</l>
               <l>To tell <hi>Ixyons Luſt</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> to <hi>Ioue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which he alreadie knew, and was inuenting,</l>
               <l>To plague <hi>Ixyon</hi> with ſome ſtrange tormenting.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:25"/>
               <l>That might into his very <hi>Soule</hi> intrude,</l>
               <l>And wound him deepe for his <hi>Ingratitude,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now the more <hi>Ixyon</hi> to annoy,</l>
               <l>Hee'le firſt delude, and afterward deſtroy:</l>
               <l>An emptie cloude he faſhions like his wife</l>
               <l>Induing it with beautie, forme, and life,</l>
               <l>So like as hee himſelfe for once did miſſe,</l>
               <l>And did the cloud in ſteed of <hi>Iuno</hi> kiſſe:</l>
               <l>With this ſame ſeeming, <hi>Iuno</hi> he preſents,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luſt</hi>-fraught <hi>Ixyon,</hi> who with an intent</l>
               <l>Not to it the leaſt accent to afford,</l>
               <l>(Knowing they'le do the deed, deny the word)</l>
               <l>Silent he haſtes vnto this borrowed ſhape,</l>
               <l>As did the Byrds t' <hi>Apelles</hi> painted grapes;</l>
               <l>But with more appetite, and bold intruſion,</l>
               <l>They did ſcarce, touch, hee taſtes of this deluſion,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:26"/>
               <l>And ioyfully hee doth himſelfe beguile,</l>
               <l>Since the true frowne was now a fained ſmile:</l>
               <l>In vtmoſt height of <hi>Luſt,</hi> and amorous twines,</l>
               <l>He clippes this ſeeming <hi>Iuno,</hi> that now ſhines</l>
               <l>Bright in his thoughts, as t'vs the eye of <hi>Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When (clad in flames) bee trottes the milky way:</l>
               <l>For in this act of <hi>Lust</hi> hee much doth toyle,</l>
               <l>But ſelfe-conſuming Lampes, that want their oyle</l>
               <l>Muſt leaue their wiſhed light, "ſated <hi>Deſire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Is like the <hi>Glowormes</hi> vneffectuall fire:</l>
               <l>But yet <hi>Ixyon</hi> on this ſeeming Faire,</l>
               <l>(Which was indeed nought but deluſiue aire)</l>
               <l>Begot the <hi>Centaures,</hi> that rebeld gainſt <hi>Ioue:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The mixture monſtrous, ſo th'effect did proue:</l>
               <l>But of <hi>Ixyons</hi> iſſue, write who will,</l>
               <l>Monſters in minde (not <hi>Nature</hi>) moue my quill,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:26"/>
               <l>This act of luſt and <hi>Horror</hi> ended thus,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioue</hi> (brooking ill a man ſo vitious</l>
               <l>As was <hi>Ixyon</hi> ſhould in <hi>Heauen</hi> remaine,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Iustice</hi> fixt him on the earth againe:</l>
               <l>Thus hee that (purg'd) among the Gods did liue,</l>
               <l>May now on earth ſuch loſſe of <hi>Glory</hi> grieue,</l>
               <l>And euer mourne to beare ſo great a croſſe</l>
               <l>"We truly nere taſte ioy, but by the loſſe,</l>
               <l>Which yet hee cannot relliſh, his dull taſt</l>
               <l>Is like one's forc't to feed that feedes his laſt,</l>
               <l>And can no whit diſtinguiſh (wanting power)</l>
               <l>But thinks what's bitter ſweet, &amp; what ſweet ſower:</l>
               <l>Hee hauing clipt this ſhape of eminence,</l>
               <l>Applaudes the act in his deluded ſence,</l>
               <l>And (ſwolne with glory of ſo great a deed)</l>
               <l>Proclaimes <hi>Heauens-Queene</hi> a whoore, to humane ſeed,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2692:27"/>
               <l>Vowing to <hi>Iupiter</hi> hee was vniuſt,</l>
               <l>And that her breſts were pillowes to his <hi>Luſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That hee in heate had clipt that world of wonder</l>
               <l>In ſpight of <hi>Ioue,</hi> and his three-forked <hi>Thunder:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which to reuenge, <hi>Ioue</hi> with his <hi>Lightning</hi> ſtrooke,</l>
               <l>This birth-curſt monſter to <hi>Hells</hi> loweſt nooke,</l>
               <l>And makes him there this heauie torment feele,</l>
               <l>Euer to turne a neuer-reſting Wheele:</l>
               <l>Which to his <hi>Oblique</hi> ſence, his crime doth ſhew</l>
               <l>In Serpents Charracter'd vnto his view,</l>
               <l>Which as he turnes, he reades, and euer turnes,</l>
               <l>And round about the poyſonous <hi>Sulphur</hi> burnes:</l>
               <l>Tha'rt in a place where thou muſt euer bee,</l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence no <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Fate</hi> can euer reſcue thee:</l>
               <l>For when on earth no man ſhall haue a brother,</l>
               <l>And th'<hi>Elements</hi> ſhall one deface each other.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2692:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
